走啊！走啊你，快走嘛！
Go, go soon
摸摸索索你真罗嗦，快走…
Knock if off, go
要死了，老鬼
Disgust, you old bastard
好了，别跟我打手势了 快走嘛！走嘛！
Enough of that, go
别忘了带瓶酒回来喔！
Don't forget to bring some wine
妈，擦屁股
I need a wipe, Mom
来
Now
哑叔，你早
Good morning, uncle
快吃啦！
Let's have a bite
哑叔！今天我留一斤白菜给你啊
There are some vegetable for you
阿坤啊！你怎么在这边玩呢？ 赶紧回去
What are you doing here? Go back home
要不然，我告诉你姊姊去
Or I'm going to tell your sister
哑叔，你早
Good morning, uncle
哑叔，哑叔，我也要去
I want to go with you, uncle
哑叔，让我去啦！
Please, uncle
这个故事从我看到哑叔的 第一眼就开始了
The story began from my first sight at uncle
那时候，我才两个月大像垃圾一样
I was only two months old like a piece of garbage
被丢在路边
And dropped on the sidewalk
理由是什么？没有人能告诉我
Nobody could tell me why
当他把我抱进怀里的时候
When he's holding me in his arms
我就再也不要离开了
I felt that I'd never leave it
因为他让我觉得温暖，安全
because he made me feel so cozy and warm
像一个父亲一样可以信赖一辈子
Just like any father to his children
她叫阿美
Her name is Ah-mei
收养她的人，妈祖菩萨会保佑你
The gods will protect whoever adopts her
可怜人拜上
From a pitiful person
哑叔生孩子了
Uncle's got a baby
哑叔生一个孩子了
我的衣服啦！
That's me my clothes
不要紧，借妹妹穿啦！
It's all-right, just a loan for your sister
手拿起来啊！来，拿给我
Take her hands, now give it to me
被给他绑好
Tit it up this way
一个男人就是这样，手脚迟钝
Men are usually all thumbs
是要怎么跟人带孩子呢？
I wonder how you could take care of a child
小孩肚子饿了，先给她喝点米汤
She's hungry, give her some porridge first
乖乖！那来的小孩？
Good baby, whose child is it?
我看看…不哭…
let me see…Don't cry, good baby
你就是输了钱才知道回来
You'll never come home till you lose your money
你看不哭了吧？
She's stopped crying
那只脏手啦！
That hand's dirty
你看你别把小孩弄哭了嘛！
Look how you made her cry
小孩不能大声说话的嘛！
Kids mustn't talk loudly
哑吧，她叫什么名字？
Does she have a name, Mute?
叫宝贝啊！
Precious
宝贝？
Precious?
俗气！俗气！不好听！换一个
That's no class, just give her another name
你不要装懂了
Don't pretend you know it
你看得懂！你看得懂你念
If you know it, then read it
你们呀！拿反了，她叫阿美
You take it at a wrong way, she's Ah-mei
对了！阿美
An-mei!
阿美 阿美     阿美
An-mei…
这个女人是怎么搞的？
What's wrong with this woman?
不要给我打手势，少来这套
Don't give me any gesture
好了，不要给我打手势了
Okay, don't give me any of your gestures
哑叔
Uncle
今天要多拿一罐啊？
You need an extra can today?
喝年奶！要补是吗？
You need some milk? For your health?
不准走
Wait a minute
死哑吧，你凶什么凶 我跟你拼了…
Want to get rough? I'll show you
我们是什么样的人家？ 养得起这个丫头吗？
How do you believe we can afford this baby?
我白天替你浆浆洗洗，烧菜煮饭
I wash and cook for you everyday
晚上还要让你翻过来调过去的
And I satisfy your desire at night
你还把我们的米酒换成 这个丫头的奶粉
But you still forget our rice wine instead
日子不要过了
What kind of life is this?
是不是玩腻了？要撵我走啊？
You tired of me? Want to chase me off?
我告诉你哑吧，打从我搬进来那天起
Ever since the day I moved in
我就后悔！我后悔跟了你这个哑吧
I hate to live with a mute like you
我后悔跟了你这个捡破烂的
I hate to live with a garbage man like you
哑吧，昨天晚上你被修理了是不是？
You got clobbered, didn't you?
哑叔被人家打
Somebody gave him a fix
哑叔，早
Good morning, uncle
哑叔，眼镜借我看
Let me see your glasses, uncle
还要补是吗？要米酒？
Need something for your health? Rice wine?
也是有道理
It stands to reason
我走了，保重，芝兰
Take care, Chih-lan, bye-bye
哑叔
Uncle
当我走进这个家以后
But when I walked into this family
我们的命运就随着改变了
Our life changed all of a sudden
我得到了一个可以倚赖一辈子的人
I got a man I could depend on all my life
却让哑叔失去了一个情感上的伴侣
But uncle lost his company who is his partner
芝兰阿姨
Auntie Chi-Ian
我想这一切都是我造成的吧！
I think it was my fault, wasn't it?
因为芝兰阿姨 曾经那么努力地尝试着爱我
Because Auntie Chi-Ian tried her best…
照顾我
Just to love me and take care of me
而我却那么爱哭，爱闹
But I was such a naughty child
芝兰阿姨从哑叔 那里再也得不到往昔的爱
I made Auntie couldn't get any love from him
因为哑叔几乎把它的全部都给了我
Because uncle's given me almost everything
谢谢各位的掌声
Thanks for the applause
现在该轮到你们台下的人上来表演了
Now it's the time for audience to perform
有谁愿意上来表演的？
Who wants to come up and perform?
来…
Come on…
他啦！他会吹小喇叭！他啦！
Him! He can play a trumpet
来，孩子我来抱
Let me hold the baby
对…你去，你去
Right…go ahead
哑叔会吹剑
He's damn good
在成长的日子里 我曾经不止一次地想过
I once thought of that many times
我跟哑叔之间其实是有着同样的命运
Me and my uncle actually had the same fate
我们都遗弃过
We both had been deserted
我被生我的人
I was deserted by who gave birth to me
他被整个动荡，流离的时代
And the whole strenuous time deserted him
他曾经拥有挚爱的父母，家园，亲人
He'd once owned his parents and his family
和芝兰阿姨
And Auntie Chi-Ian
而转眼之间
But all of a sudden
除了思念，什么都不在了
Nothing existed but his heart
也许他曾经把我当成自己生命的延续
He might take me as his continuity of life
就像我浑沌未开的心灵中
Just like that chaos of my heart
早已经把它当成一个至高无上
Took it as something couldn't take place
无法取代的形象一样
Just like a supreme being in the days gone
然而 我却都没有办法用言语来表达…
But we couldn't talk to each other with words
哑吧，拜祖先啊！
Worshipping your ancestors!
阿美     阿美     阿美
Ah-mei
到我们家去吃年夜饭
Come to my house for New Year's dinner
你客气什么呢？
Be my guest
今天晚上咱们哥俩喝个痛快儿
Let's have a good drink today
你不给面子吗？
You aren't doing me favor, are you?
哑叔，哑叔，你看阿美
Take a look at Ah-mei, uncle
快叫爸爸，阿美，叫爸爸
Go tell Dad, Ah-mei
快点！阿美叫爸爸，爸爸
Ah-mei, hurry up, go and tell Dad
她不会也是个哑吧？
I wonder if she's mute too
你在胡说些什么？没人教当然是不会
What are you talking about?
阿满就是爱乱说话，你不要生气喔？
Ah-man's always a big mouth, don't be mad
阿明，我们回去了
Let's go home
哑叔，等一下一定要来喔！
Be sure to come over later, uncle
直到那一天，也许是阿明的引导
Until that day, it might be Ah-ming's hint
更也许是上天的催促
Or it might be help from heaven
我生平的第一句话是
My first word in my life is…
爸爸
Dad
哑叔来…请坐…
This way, sit down please
怎么了！他说什么嘛？
What happened? What did he say?
阿美会叫爸爸了是不是？
Ah-mei can say Daddy
乌鸦养凤凰会叫了！
A phoenix raised by a crow can talk
阿美会叫爸爸了剑
Ah-mei knows how to say Daddy
来…叫爸爸
Now, say daddy
爸爸
Daddy
阿美，叫爸爸了
Ah-mei, you're wonderful
哑吧     哑吧
Mute
阿满叔
Uncle
阿美做功课啊！
Improving your mind!
来啊…快来啊！
Come on
哑吧，今天立冬进点补吧
It's winter beginning, let's have extra natty
有一道菜，我老婆不会做
There's one dish my wife can't make
你能不能帮忙？
Can you help with it?
吃香肉啊！
Dog meat!
对不起了小狗，早死早投胎
Sorry, doggie, I'll help you be reincarnated
下辈子到洋人家里面喝牛奶，睡沙发
You'll belong to a foreign family
还外带美容呢！
That'll make your next life better
爸爸，有狗在叫她？是谁家的？
There's a dog barking, whose dog is it?
阿美，没你的事，做功课呢？
None of your business, go back your homework
快把开水倒进盆里
Just put it into the pan
快…好了…
By the way…
狗怎么不见了！你搁那儿了？
Where's the dog? Where did you put it?
爸爸
Dad
爸，你看好可怜哦！头上都是血
How pitiful, there's blood all over its head
爸，我们把它留下来好不好？
Let's keep it, okay?
不行啊！我们要吃
No, we want to eat it
阿明     阿美 阿美
Ah-mei
阿明，你看我们家新养的狗
Ah-ming, we've got a dog
好可爱的狗喔！
What a cute dog
它的头上怎么都是血啊？
Why is its head all bloody?
我也不知道，大概是被坏人打的
I don't know, somebody hit it, I guess
好可怜哦！我们来给它擦药
Let's put some medicine on it
好
Okay
轻一点哦！小心，小心
Easy, be careful
爸，狗流血痛不痛？
Does it hurt when a dog's bleeding, Daddy?
废话，当然痛啦！
Nuts, of course it hurts
我又没有问你
I'm not asking you
对，人家又没问你
Yeah, she's not asking you
你少噜嗦
You shut up
你干什么嘛？
What do you think you're doing?
爸爸，放学来接我 要不要？要不要嘛？
Meet me after school is over, okay?
酒干倘卖呒？
Any bottle for sell?
爸，我要下车
I want to get off
阿美，不要这样子嘛！
Come on, Ah-mei
有什么事你告诉我阿明 我一定替你摆平
Just tell me what the matter is
酒干倘卖呒？
Any bottle for sell?
你怎么推人啊你，你还咬我，我打你
How dare you push and bite me, I'll show you back
阿明，你看
Look, Ah-ming
刘俊杰！你干什么？不要跑
What're you doing, Liu Chun-chieh? Stop
刘俊杰，回来！你不要跑，站住
Come back, Liu Chun-chieh
阿明，不要让他跑掉了
Ah-ming, don't let him get away
刘俊杰，不要跑
你不要走
我打死你，打，打
阿明
Ah-ming
阿明，你看
Ah-ming, look
阿美
Ah-mei
来福，来福加油，加油
Go, go, Lau-fu
来福
Lai-fu
咬死它…
Bite hime to death
来福
Lai-fu
来福，咬死它…
Lai-fu, kill him
来福，好棒哦！
You're great, Lai-fu
来福！乖！
Good boy, Lai-fu
来福好乖！    死了没有？
Good boy, Lai-fu Is it dead?
不知道剑
I don't know
到底死了没有？
Is it dead anyway?
死了
It's dead
妈
Mom
丢掉！快丢掉！ 干什么？
Just drop it What's wrong?
好了…小孩嘛！
Come on, it's a kid
以后不能这样
Don't do that again
好啦！
Okay
乖乖，两斤多！
Good, over two catties
来…别急！
Come on, take it easy
阿美，它吓你，你吃它
It scared you, so you can eat it
我不要吃
No, I don't
有没有毒啊？到底有没有毒啊？!
Is it poisonous? Isn't it?
吃了才知道，哑吧，你吃一块
Don't know till we eat it, have some, mute
吃
Eat
爸爸，你怎么了？
What's the matter with you? Dad
怎么了？到底是怎么了？
What's the matter, Dad?
爸爸
Dad
死小子，一出门就不知道进门
You never know when to come in once you come out
好像水流的破布一样
Like a rag in a stream
你鬼鬼崇崇的干什么？
What are you sneaking around for?
一天到晚晃过来晃过去的
Fooling around all day long
阿坤，别怕！有什么事情跟姊姊说
It's okay, just tell me about it
我拿这给阿美
I brought this to Ah-mei
谢谢
Thank you!
不要脸，男生爱女生
Shame on you, a man loves a woman
我的呢？
What about mine?
没有了
No more
小气鬼！
Stingy
臭阿明，你才小气呢？
No, you're stingy
你为什么不送我东西？
Why don't you give me a present?
我又没有钱怎样给你买玩具嘛！
I've got no money to buy toys for you
舅舅是大人 他当然应该给我买东西啊
He is an adult, he should buy me something
不要脸
Shame on you
你才不要脸呢！
No, you're shameless
好了，好了，不要吵！你们听我说
Stop it, just listen to me
阿明，阿坤一个人一部小车车
Ah-ming, Ah-kun, one car for each
阿美一个洋娃娃
A doll for Ah-mei
哑吧一项毛线帽
A wool hat for mute
妈妈一条项炼
A necklace for Mom
钱呀！钱…
Money… money
你又在干什么？!
What are you doing now?
没有没有，我今天运气一定好
Nothing, I think I've got some luck today
我拿走了
I'm taking it
阿满，那是要给人的会钱 是别人的会钱
That money belongs to somebody else
拿回来还我
Give it to me
我今天晚上会很快就回来了嘛！
I'll be back soon tonight
加倍还给你，走了
I'll give it back twice as much as this amount
你这短命的，赌什么？赌要死啊？
Why must you gamble? It's dangerous
那么爱赌，赌死算了
Go to hell
通吃…
Take it all
下…不敢下的是狗熊
Bets…or you're a coward
赌了一千八百多次了 总该让我赢一次吧
I've lost so much, I should win once
王八过门槛，全凭这一翻
Everything depends on this
凶娘们，老骂我爱赌
You always rant at my gambling
赢条金项炼塞你的嘴
I'll stop your mouth with a gold necklace
今天晚上让你喊我亲爱的
And I'll make you call me darling tonight
回去了，都看了几百遍了
Go home, you've read that a hundred times
要你管啊？
None of your business
不回去了
I'm not going back
要你管啊！
You keep out of this
洋娃娃，你还会跑？
Pretty, dolly, you've run away?
游泳去了！
Went swimming
回来…小心小心
Come back…
回来…
看你往那儿跑？回来…
You won't get away, come back
满嫂…快点！
Auntie, come on, oh, my God
满嫂啊！糟了…
阿满他，他在水沟边
He's by the gutter, Ah-man
阿满…
Ah-man…
满嫂…
Auntie…
姊姊…
Sister…
阿满…
Ah-man…
夭筹短命
Must you torture me this way?
你一定要这样折磨我
才高兴是不是？你说是不是？
That makes you happy, doesn't it?
我不是真的咒你，不是真的要骂你
I didn't really mean to scold you
你知道吗？
You know that?
我不是真的要你去死
I didn't really want you to die
阿满嫂家里失火了
Auntie's house is on fire
我不是真的叫你去死…
I didn't want you to die…
满嫂，先回去啦！
Auntie, come on and go home
你再不回去，家里要烧光了
House will burn down if you still stay here
你不回去，家是会被烧光了
The house will burn down if you still stay here
你那个傻小弟还在家里
You silly brother still sleeps in it
要是被烧死了，怎么办？
What will you do if he's burned?
阿美
Ah-mei
阿美，阿美…
阿美，阿美…等一等
Ah-mei, wait a minute
爸爸…
Dad…
妈，妈，放开我…
Mom, let me go, I want to find my Mom
我要找我妈妈…
妈妈…
Mom…
我的宝贝儿子，不要哭，妈在这边
My little baby, don't cry, Mon's here
妈妈…
Mom…
爸爸跟舅舅呢？
爸爸…
Dad…
凶猛，炙热的火光，死亡的阴影
Hat hot and fierce light, shadow of death
满嫂失神无助的脸孔 痛哭呼救的哀号
Helpless crying and miserable look from Auntie
似乎成了我童年惨痛恐怖的记忆
Seems like it became a memory of my childhood
但是烈火烧去了一切
Though terrible fire burned everything up
却烧不掉希望
It couldn't burn our hope
人总会活下去的
People have to go on living anyway
苦难通常使一个人忘记昨天
Misery makes a man forget about yesterday
而踏实地活在今天的劳累中
It makes people live in today's fatigue
于是任它季节更替物换星移
No matter how fast time would pass
日子对我们来说都是一样的
Everyday to us is the same
一样的邻居朋友，一样的作夜息
The same neighbors and friends, the same work
直到某一天
Until one day…
当我蓦然发觉爸爸怎么白发斑驳 一脸皱纹
Suddenly I found something white in my father's head
那个时候，我才发现我已经长大了
Then I found that I'm grown up
而且一个崭新的奇异的世界
And a strange now world has tied us together
已经在不知不觉中 把我们紧紧的围住了
So secretly and so tightly
小老鼠，快点啦！
Come on, little mouse
老大，急什么又不是跟阿美结婚
It's not a marriage with Ah-mei
再罗嗦，我扁你喔！
Shut up or I'll fix you
阿明！ 你买那么多菜是要办酒席是吗？
You bought that much food for a feast?
阿美今天第一天上班，给她庆祝一下
To celebrate her first day at work
你看我家阿明啊！ 比那上班的人还要紧张
Ah-ming's more anxious than she is
哑叔，你看
Look, uncle
哑叔
Uncle
不用了…今天我赚了一点外快
It's okay, I've made some extra money today
不要客气啦！
Don't get mad, Uncle
是不是又遇到一个阔寡妇呀？
You'd run into another rich window, didn't you?
你不要乱讲话，我可没跟她干什么
Don't talk nonsense, I've got nothing to do with her
我只不过说她长的很漂亮
I only say that she's beautiful
真的很漂亮？
Is she beautiful
当然！跟你长得差不多啦！
Sure she is, beautiful as you
阿明，阿美到底是几多点下班？
When does Ah-mei finish her work?
我来炒两样小菜，我们来吃宵夜
Let me make some dishes for our snack
给我一道
Give me a ray of warming light
温柔的光
莫在今宵
Don't maintain that you're in a stupor
强说迷惘
和我一起
Dance with me to our heart's desire
尽情舞蹈
陌生的人
How much loneliness does a stranger have
寂寞多少
再听一听，叮叮当当
Listen again-ding dong, ding dong
那里来的音符真教人心伤
How the distant notes pierce my heart
再唱一唱Do Be Do Wa
Sing again - do be do wa
想学我的模样就别再心伤
Feeling of sorrow if you'd like to stimulate
我送你回家好不好？
I'll take you home, okay?
我刚才不是故意的
I didn't mean it just now
我说你唱的不好是真的
But it's true you don't sing well
你不要生气嘛！女孩子要有风度
Don't be angry, act like a lady
难道你唱得不好 还要我说你唱得好啊
You want me to lie about your singing?
这样不是太虚伪了吗？
Wouldn't that be pretty vain?
好了好了，你唱得好 你唱得比谁都好
Okay, you sing very well, better than anybody
比邓丽君都好，可以了吧？
Even better than Teresa Teng, satisfy?
我警告你，你没有资格批评我
You have no right to criticize me
我是没资格批评你
True, I have no right
不过你唱得好不 我一听就听出来了
But I can tell if you sing well or not
我是作曲的 我想我可以给你一点意见
I'm a composer, I can give you some advice
岂有此理，你这个死仔 你是怎么开车的
下车，下车，打你一顿才行
岂有此理，怎么开车的
你的车
You car
没关系，倒霉的不是我 是借车给我的朋友
It's okay, too bad for the owner, though
上车
Get in
后来这条歌居然红了
Later on the song became a hit
爸，我回来了
I'm home, Dad
爸，我给你介绍 他是时君迈，是作曲的
Dad, he's Shin Chun-mai, a song writer
这是我爸爸
My Dad
来福，不要这么没礼貌
Don't be so rude, Dai-fu
要不要到我们家坐坐？
Want to come to my house and sit for a while
不用了，以后有的是机会，拜拜
No…there'll be opportunities later
拜
Good-bye
来福，我们回家吧！
Let's go home, Lai-fu
爸，走吧！
Let's go, Dad
爸，我告诉你，刚刚的时君迈
That Shin Chun-mai I just mentioned, Dad
他说他有好多首新歌
He said he's got some new songs
要我唱他的歌剑∷要亲自教我
Which fits me and he wants to teach me personally
我好开心啊！
I'm so happy
爸，我跟你讲啊
Dad, you know something
刚才唱歌好有意思剑
I like singing very much
来了
Here it is
爸，你先吃嘛！
Go ahead, Dad
一早就喝酒，你不开车了
Drinking so early, you are not driving, are you?
妈，你不要管我
Leave me alone, Mom
什么！你说什么，你说什么…
What do you think you are?
我们大伙住这 已经住了…，三十年了
Much of us have lived here for thirty years
你一叫我们搬，我们就得搬啊？
Where did you have us move to?
你们大家来评评理
Please give a fin comment, you guys
叫我们搬家，是要搬到那里去
Where did you want us move to?
搬去绿岛，是不是？
To Green Island?
怎么了？菊嫂，怎么回事吗？
What's the matter, Auntie?
违章建筑是一定要拆的
The illegal building must be torn down
政府要你们搬家 一定会给你们补助的嘛
The government will make up for you
大人呀！别说笑了
What a joke
补助的钱啊！只能买两个杨杨米
Money is only enough to buy two pieces of candy
骗我们不懂啊？
What do you take me for, a child?
国民住宅，你们可以优先登记呀！
You have preference for government housing
什么优先登记？ 优先登记还要等一两年
Preference? It'll still take a year or more
站好
Stand still
不要激动嘛！ 我只是吃公家饭替政府做事
Listen, I just work for the government
我也跟你们一样，住在这里呀！
I live here too the same as you guys
你跟我们一样？
Just like us
你们自己人，所以可以优先登记
The government preference and have priority
就是啊！ 你们自己的人当然是自己维护自己人
The government will protect only those who are the same
叫别人搬家，这样有道理吗？
How can you tell other people to move
你们大家评评理，这种人不打怎么行
Such a man like him needs a good lesson
一群疯狗，我告诉你们
A bunch of mad dogs, I'm telling you…
要是不搬的话，就别怪我不客气
If you don't move out, I'll get rough with you
什么不客气？你想欺负我们吗？
What do you mean by that? get rough with us
你别跑！别跑！
Don't run away
打！
Beat him
你跟我凶什么凶？我早就想打人了
Why me? I want to beat somebody too
我告诉你 昨天晚上我就想打人了啦！
I wanted to beat somebody last night
你给我回来
Come back
等一下…
Wait a minute…
我叫你进来，走了
I told you to come in, let' go
爸，不要不开心嘛！
Don't be unhappy, Dad
拆房子是大家的事 又不是光拆我们的
Our house isn't the only one to be torn down
大不了，搬家就是了嘛！
Anyway, we'll have to move
钱！爸，你不要担心
Don't worry about the money, Dad
我以后一定会 赚很多很多钱给你买房子的
I'll make a lot of money for you to buy a house
我踩着不变的步伐
I walk with unvarying footsteps
是为了配合你到来
Waiting for your coming
在慌张迟疑的时候
When you have anxiety and doubt
请跟我来
Please come with me
我带着梦幻的期待
I carry a dreamlike hope
是无法按捺的情怀
A feeling that can't be repressed
在你不注意的时候
When you are distracted
请跟我来
Please come with me
别说什么
It's world you cannot foresee
那是你无法预知的世界
别说，你不用说
You don't have to say anything
你的眼睛已经告诉了我
Your eyes have already told me
当
当春雨飘呀飘的飘在
When spring showers are drifting down
你滴也滴不完的发梢
And dripping endlessly from your hair
戴着你的水晶珠炼
Wear your crystal pearl necklace
请跟我来
Please come with me
别说什么
It's world you cannot foresee
那是你无法预知的世界
别说，你不用说
You don't have to say anything
你的眼睛已经告诉了我
Your eyes have already told me
当春雨飘呀飘的飘在
When spring showers are drifting down
你滴也滴不完的发梢
And dripping endlessly from your hair
戴着你的水晶珠链
Wear your crystal pearl necklace
请跟我来
Please come with me
孙小姐
I hope you could
广泰娱乐公司的经理 余广泰先生要见你
The Manager Yu of Kuang Tail wants to see you
没关系，你不要怕 他不会对你有兴趣
Don't be afraid, he has no interest in you
只对男人有兴趣，走
He has interest only in men
我来介绍这位是…
Let me introduce…
我早就认识了 她就是大名鼎鼎的歌星沈妮
I know her, she's the famous singer star, Shen-ni
我好喜欢听你的歌哦！
I like your singing very much
谢谢
Thank you!
这位是我的好朋友时君迈
This is my friend Shin Chun-mai
我们早就认识了，我是她的经纪人
I knew each other before, I'm her manager
我刚才听过你的歌 我觉得你很有前途
I just heard you sang, you'll have a good future
这是我的名片
Here's my name card
明天有空的话，我想跟你谈一谈
I'd like to talk to you tomorrow
余广泰 我的下一张唱片什么时候出啊？
When will my next record be released?
沈妮，你上张唱片己经卖得不好了
Your last record didn't sell well
我看，你暂时先做做秀吧！可是…
I think you'd better offer some shows nowadays
经理，孙小姐来了
Manager, Miss Shen's here
沈妮，我有重要事情要谈
I've got something to discuss with you
你先出去一下好吗？
You leave for a while, okay?
沈姐姐
Sister Shen
孙小姐，我希望你取代沈妮
I hope you could take Shen-ni's place
为什么？
Why?
观众需要新的刺激，新的面孔
The audience needs some new excitements, new faces
沈妮那一套，观众早已经看腻了
They tired of Shen-ni now
你的条件比她好多了
Your qualifications are better
我有这个条件吗？
Do you think I'm qualified?
你觉得沈妮有条件吗？
Do you think she's qualified?
她以前不过是个舞小姐 连国语都说不好
She was a dancer, she couldn't speak Chinese
所以呀条件不在你，是在我
The qualifications depend on me, not you
只要你什么都听我的安排
You just do whatever I tell you…
我保证你将来一定比沈妮还红
And you'll be bigger than she is
好，我答应你
Okay, I agree
不过我有一个条件
But I have a requirement
有什么条件？
What's that?
我要他帮我作曲
I want him to compose for me
时先生，很抱歉，恕我直言
Mr. Shin, I'm sorry, I have 10 tell you the true
我们要的是雅俗共赏的商业歌曲
What we need are commercial songs
而不是你那种自弹自唱的民谣歌曲
Not those folk songs, like yours
孙小姐，这点我很坚持
That's what I insist, Miss Sun
我希望你考虑，考虑
I hope you'll think it over
余广泰是什么东西？
What does he think he is?
GA丫，市侩，俗气
Gay, a shark, vulgar
你看沈妮唱了多少歌 那一条是有水准的
None of Shen-ni's songs has class
我才没那么无聊替他作曲
Would I write those stupid songs?
他那种钱啊！我不稀罕
I don't care these money he earned
如果你喜欢你跟他去好了
If you like him, go with him
我只是想多赚点钱 买栋房子给我爸爸
I just want to make more money and buy my father a house
让他生活过得好一点
That'll make him a better life
难道我这样做也错了吗？
Am I doing wrong?
如果你不喜欢 我现在就可以打电话拒绝他
I you don't like it, I'll give him a call right now
我想你还是答应他
Maybe you should go along with him
好，袁小姐，麻烦你
Okay, thanks for your trouble, Miss Yuen
哪里
It's nothing, nothing
我们现在完成了第一步
Now we've finished the first step
第二步，我要替你改个名子
And the second is to change your name
改个名字啊？
Change my name?
对！改个名字就是换一个人
Yes, just like making a new person
从现在开始，你的名字叫做孙瑞琪
From now on your name is Sun Jui-chi
孙瑞琪
Sun Jui-chi
还有，我已经替你 租了一栋很舒适的房子
By the way, I've rent a very comfortable room for you
明天你就可以搬进去住
You can move in tomorrow
为什么？
Why?
因为我要把你捧成歌星中的名星
Because I want to make you a star of all stars
我要告诉传播界
I'll inform the mass media
说你是在富有 而有教养的家庭中长大
You grow up from a wealthy and cultured family
我要你充满了大家闺秀的气质
And make you full of the manner of a fine lady
让所有的观众看得到，而摸不着
Something the audience can see, not touched
哑叔，你真的答应阿美搬出去住啊？
You're allowing Ah-mei to move out
我跟你说，现在当歌星得危险啊！
It's dangerous to be a singer these days
那些有钱人一天到晚在打歌星的主意
Rich men are always after them
不行，不行哪！小老鼠，你说
It won't do, you say it, mouse
好
Okay
哑叔，你每天收旧报纸
You collect newspaper everyday
你没有看报上说啊！
Don't you read what's in them?
那些坏人啊最喜欢绑架那些女歌星了
Bad guys like to abduct singers
把她们的衣服剥光，拍裸体照
Take their clothes off and photograph them
就像什么封面女郎什么的？
Like that Spin-up Girl case
真的她！
It's really
阿明，你要我说的我都说了
An-ming, I said what you wanted
做歌星那有什么不好？
What's wrong to be a star?
以后要是出了名，找一个有钱人
Get famous and find a rich man
到那个时候，钱比米都多喔！
You'll have more money than rice
哑叔到那个时候 吃，穿都不用烦恼了
Uncle will have everything then
对啦！
That's right
到时候 连你这个爸爸都不会认了啦！
Then she won't recognize her own father
阿明，你不要胡说
I don't think Ah-mei's like that
我想阿美她不是那种人
Don't be silly, Ah-ming
她只是想多赚一点钱
She just wants to make some money
爸，我回来了
Dad, I'm back
东西在那儿
My stuff is there
阿美，你爸爸等你吃饭，等了很久了
Your father is waiting so long, for having dinner with you
爸爸，我不能在家里吃饭了
I can't eat at home, Dad
公司安排我今天要跟记者
The company's arranged a party
还有唱片公司的老板一起吃饭
With reporters and the record company boss
吃完饭，我还要练歌呢！
I have to practice singing after dinner
但爸爸你放心 我一定会常常回来看爸爸的
But I'll come and see you often, Dad
再见
Good-bye
什么时候儿时玩伴都离我远去
When did the frog croaks become memory
什么时候身旁的人已不再熟悉
When did the land become so crowded
人潮的拥挤，拉开了我们的距离
With tall buildings towering all around
沉默的大地
And neon signs making the night so harsh
把地面的夜晚默默的吐气
谁能告诉我，谁能告诉我
Who can tell me? Who can tell?
是我们改变了世界
Did we change the world
还是世界改变了我
Or did the world change you and me?
和你
一样的月光
The same moonlight
一样的照着新店溪
Shines on the same Hsintien River
一样的冬天
The same winter
一样的下着冰冷的雨
Brings the same cold rains
一样的尘埃
The same dust
一样的在风中堆积
Is blown by the same wind
一样的笑容
The same smiles
一样的泪水
The same tears
一样的日子
The same days
一样的我和你
The same you and me
一样的笑容
The same smiles
一样的泪水
The same tears
一样的日子
The same days
一样的我和你
The same you and me
阿美还真漂亮剑
Ah-ming's really beautiful
真好听，真好听
Sounds really good
哑叔，你可以放心了，是不是？
You don't have to worry now, do you?
你看阿美实在真行啊！
See? Ah-ming's really wonderful
她一定会变成一个很红很红的歌星
She'll be a very popular singer
谢谢，谢谢
Thank you, thank you
请问孙小姐 听说你生长在一个大家庭
I hear you grew up on a wealthy family
请问你父亲做什么生意的？
What business is your father in?
我父亲…
My father…
她父亲是个大建筑商
Her father's a big contractor
现在全家移民到美国去了
He's emigrated to America now
只留下孙小姐一个人在国内
Only Miss Sun is left here
请问孙小姐 你一个人在国内都做些什么
How do you make a living here, Miss Sun
那要看我的经纪人怎么安排了？
It depends on my manager's arrangement
明天孙小姐就要到东南亚巡回演唱吧
She stars a Southeast Asian tour tomorrow
一月以后再回国
She'll be back in a month
到时候将会举办一个 全国最大型的演唱会
The she'll have the biggest concert here
孙小姐，问你个题外话
Let me ask an irrelevant question?
你有没有比较亲密的男朋友啊？
Do you have a close boy friend?
到底有没有啊？
Well? Do you?
有啊！很多，只要是爱护我的观众
Yes, a lot of them, my listeners
都是我最亲密的朋友
My listeners are my closest friends
其实你最近身体不太好 根本就不应该出来
You aren't well, shouldn't come out
阿美也太过份了
Ah-mei's gone too far
搬出去这么久才回来看你两三次
Only coming back so rarely to see you
开记者招待会也不来邀请你 太不像话了
Not asking you to her press conference
等一下看到她，一定要问问她
When I see her, I'll ask her about that
你这个人怎么搞的？
What's the matter with you?
你不是那个大歌星沈妮呢？
Aren't you that great singer, Shen-ni?
我就是那个大歌星沈妮
Yes, I'm that great singer
怎么，要不要签名啊？
Why? You want my antograph
拿笔来啊？
Give me a pen
我又不是你的歌迷 我们是来找阿美的
I'm not your friend, I came to see Ah-mei
什么阿美不阿美的？
Who's Ah-mei?
阿美就是孙瑞琪嘛！
Ah-mei's Sun Jui-chi
孙瑞琪？
Sun Jui-chi
孙瑞琪有什么了不起的？
What's so great about her?
她的歌那能跟我比啊？
How can her singing compare with mine?
她只不过比我年轻，漂亮
She's just younger and prettier, that's all
一个人不可能永远年轻漂亮的
Nobody's young and pretty forever
总有一天，她也会掉下来
Anyway one day she'll fall
永远都爬不起来！
Then she'll never come up again
你讲话要客气一点喔！
Be careful about what you say
什么客气不客气？你跟她什么关系？
So what? What's she to you?
当然有关系啦！我是她邻居呀！
I'm her neighbor, that's all
他是她爸爸啊！
He's her father
他是她爸爸？开玩笑
He's her father? That's laugh
真的啊！他真的是她爸爸
It's true, he's really her father
各位！各位！大家静一静
Attention, everybody, quiet, please
我现在告诉你们一个好消息
I have some good news for you
他就是孙瑞琪的爸爸
He's Sun Jui-chi's father
刚从美国回来的爸爸
Her father, just back from America
大建筑商的爸爸，刚刚从美国回来的
The big contractor, back from America
你们看一看，就是这个样子的
See? That's the way it is
各位！他不是她爸爸
He isn't her father, folks
你们看，他像她爸爸吗？
Does he look like him?
他们俩个只不过是热情的观众而已
They're just enthusiastic fans
什么热情的观众？他真的是她爸爸
What? He's really her father
你想行骗是吗？
You're trying to pull a fast one?
行骗！你才行骗呢！
You're the fraud
阿美，阿美，你跟他讲
Tell them, Ah-mei
他是不是你爸爸？你说啊！
Isn't he your father? Speak up
你们看 他自己都不承认是孙瑞琪的爸爸
See? Even he doesn't say it
他们两个不是骗子是什么？骗子
If they're not frauds, what are they?
阿美，你过来，你过来
Ah-mei, come here
你跟他们说，你跟他们说他是你爸爸
Tel them he's your father
你怎么不说？
Why don't you speak up?
阿美，不行！我求你
No, Ah-mei, please
阿美，你就听我这一次
Listen to me, just this once
爸爸，对不起
Dad, I'm sorry
少来这一套 现在说对不起已经太晚了啊
It's too late to say that now
你现在很拽了 看不起我们了是不是？
You're popular and you despite us now
谁看不起你们嘛？
Who despite you?
阿明，你不要胡闹好不好？
Don't say silly things, Ah-ming
你说我胡闹，你娘的！
Me said silly things? Dame you
阿明，不要这样嘛！
Don't be that way
好…阿美 …十多年来只得到你这句话
Over 20 years and this is what I get
我真的没有看不起你们嘛！
I really don't despise you
我们不配和你在一起了 现在你是大歌星
You're star, we're not on the level as high as you
没有
No…
阿明，你少讲两句
Ah-ming, don't talk so much
现在你可以走了
You can go now
你根本就不属于我们这里的
You don't belong here
没有你，我们一样过啦
We can get along without you
你本来就是捡来的
You're just a foundling, anyway
阿明，你说完了没有？
Are you finished, Ah-ming?
阿美…
Ah-mei
我从小看阿美长大
I watched Ah-mei grow up
我相信她不是那种人，我对她有信心
She isn't like that, I believe in her…
你自己血压高，不要再喝酒了
Stop drinking, your high blood pressure
我们也许曾经相知，相爱
Ah-mei, we may have loved once
但是，爱情与恩情是有分别的
But love and friendship are different
我想你了解我的意思
You know what I mean
抱歉，我走了，时君迈
Sorry, I'm leaving, Shi Chun-mai
想起初相见似地转天旋
Think how the earth shook when we met
当意念改变
And then the changes, like passing mists
如过眼云烟
在季节变换的天空里
As the seasons change in he heavens
你游游荡荡不已
You wander without end
在星月移动的夜空下 星马，香港，会有人照顾你的
Under the sky with its traveling orbs People will entertainment you in Singapore and Hong Kong
台北我实在分不开身
I can't leave here
没关系，我会照顾自己的
I can take care of myself
好，我先预祝你这次巡回演唱成功
Okay, good luck on your tour
对了！ 你不要忘了吧…十万交给我爸爸
Don't forget, give Dad two hundred thousand
他需要这笔钱买房子
He needs it to buy a house
好，我尽快把钱送去
Okay, I'll send it to him
谢谢，我先走了
Thanks, good-bye
就把我不愿想起的过去
I'll cast aside unwanted memories
丢向天际
Far away, they lose their mystery
一览无遗
不再神秘
想起初相见
Think how the earth shook when we met
似地转天旋
当意念改变
And then the changes, like passing mists
如过眼云烟
在季节变换的天空里
As the seasons change in the heavens
你游游荡荡不已
You wander without end
在星月移动的夜空下
Under the sky with its traveling orbs
像迷迷蒙蒙轻纱
In a gauss like haze
我一不小心失去的情感
I was careless, lost my love
说来遗憾
Much to my regret
就把我不愿想起的过去
I'll cast aside unwanted memories
丢向天际
Far away, they lose their mystery
一览无遗
不再神秘
想起初相见
Think how the earth shook when we met
似地转天旋
当意念改变
And then the changes, like passing mists
如过眼云烟
想起初相见
Think how the earth shook when we met
似地转天旋
当意念改变
And then the changes, like passing mists
如过眼云烟
当如雷的掌声响起时
When thunder-like applause came
我知道这一切都是我的
I knew it was all mine
我应该兴奋，感动
I should be moved and excited
但是没有人知道
But nobody knows that…
在这一刹那间 我却更加的孤单，寂寞
I felt so lonely at that moment
因为台下没有一位是我想看到的人
Nobody down there is who I wanted to see
他们都在千里之外
They're all thousand miles away
没有救了，人道毁灭了
It's hopeless, humanity is dead
爸，你看好可怜哦！头上都是血
He's pitiful, his head's all bloody
来福，我们回家
Let's go home, Lai-fu
孙先生
Mr Sun
孙先生，那天晚上很抱歉
I'm sorry about that night, Mr. Sun
这里是…十万，是阿美要我交给你的
She wants you to have this two hundred thousand
她说要你先买房子
It's to buy a house with
其实，阿美也很想念你
She misses you very much
她说等香港演唱会一完 马上就回来看你
She'll visit you when she comes back
我有句话一直想对你说
There's something I want to tell you
阿美很幸运，她红的很快
She's lucky, she's got popular fast
像她现在这样子
A lot of girls dream about…
是很多女孩子所追求的梦想
Being the way she is now
我希望你能成全她
I hope you'll give her your help
下来下来吧
阿明啊…
放开我，放开我
Ah-ming
阿明…
快叫救护车…
Call an ambulance
李亚明先生
Taxi driving is the job he owned
服务计程车
违建拆除
Killed in tearing an illegal building
意外丧生
灵前公祭
Totally joining his funeral with our respect
敬达哀忱
魂兮不昧
His soul will live with us forever
来格来歆
呜呼
God bless him
哀哉
尚飨
行三鞠躬礼
Bow to him with utmost heartiness
一鞠躬
First bow
再鞠躬
Second bow
三鞠躬
Third bow
义弟答谢
I own you my thanks
礼成
Ceremony concluded
满嫂
Mouse and I are going back to Tai-tung
我跟老鼠后天就要回台东老家
如果有空，我会回台北看你
We'll come to see you when we have time
阿明…
Ah-ming
先到信义路我家
First to my home on Hsinyi Road
不！先回阳明山
No, to Yangmingshan first
你不是答应我 让我先回家看我爸爸的吗
Didn't you agree to let me see Dad first
阿美，过两天演唱会就要开始了
Your concert will begin in two days
你还是专心排练
Concentrate on your practice
相信我，你爸爸我会照顾他的
Trust me to take care of your father
阿美，这场演唱会对你 对我都很重要
This concert is important to us
今年度最受欢迎的红歌星孙瑞琪小姐
The best singer of the year Miss Sun Jui-chi
日前搭乘华航班机返抵国门
She's returned by taking CAL
老板娘，给我一碗牛肉面，一瓶啤酒
Beef noodles and a beer, Mamasan
马上来
Right away
孙瑞琪小姐是接受了 星加坡电视台的邀请
She accepted the invitation from Singapore Television
演出非常成功
It was a very successful tour
可以说轰动了整个东南亚
Now she's come back to Taiwan
这一次回国 是为了响应盲哑协会的邀请
The invitation of the Deal-Mute
在八月十五号举行 她个人的慈善演唱会
For a charity concert on Aug 15
我们相信以她歌唱的才华行善的热忱
Her talent and charitable generosity
必将在国中歌坛 造成另一次更大的轰动
Really impress on the Taiwan entertainmet
你认识阿美啊？
Do you know Ah-mei?
请问，你知不知道这里的人 都搬到那儿去了？
Where did the people here move to?
我也不知道，你来找人吗？
Don't know, you're looking for somebody?
有个老朋友，…十几年没见了
An old friend I haven't seen for 20 years
想看一看他
I want to see him
没想到，这里已经变成这个样子
But this place has changed so much
我先走了
Good-bye
阿美，阿美，到处找不到你
Ah-mei, I've been looking for you all day already
我就知道你跑到这儿来了
Finally, I guess you came here
你怎么给我交待？
What have you to say about this?
什么时候变成这样子，我也不知道
I don't when this happened
我要去找我爸爸
I want to find my father
阿美，…十万我早已经交给你爸爸了
I gave him the money, like you said
他会照顾他自己
He can take care of himself
演唱会就要开始了 我们时间已经不够了
We have to prepare for the concert
你要宣传，排练，参加记者招待会
You have a press conference too
我们有太多太多的事情要做
We've got too many things to do
阿美，你不能这样毁了你自己呀
You can't destroy yourself this way
就算我求你好不好？
I'm begging
还好阿美出国前留下了一笔钱
It's luck Ah-mei left that money
阿明的丧事和我开的面摊 都是用她这笔钱
It covered Ah-ming's funeral, the noodle store
日子还算过得去
We can get by
就是哑叔他整天想着阿美
Uncle thinks of Ah-mei all day
虽然他不说，我也看得出来
He doesn't say so, but I can tell
所以我就陪他住在一起
So I live with him
哑叔最近身体也不好
His health isn't good lately
住在一起比较好照顾
I can't take care of him, living there
反正年纪也大了，也不怕人家说闲话
I'm too old to care what people say
哑叔又在吹了
Uncle's blowing again
阿美小的时候一哭 哑叔就用这个声音逗她
He used to soothe Ah-mei that way
她的眼泪还来不及 擦就笑得好可爱哦！
That would make her laugh, so cute
自从阿美出国以后
Since Ah-mei went abroad
哑叔每天都要吹好几次
Uncle blows all the time
我突然想做一件事
There something
对不起，我不进去了，帮我问候哑叔
Say hello to uncle for me
阿美回来了
Ah-mei's come back
她刚回国一定很忙 过两天我就去找她
I'll go see her in a couple of days
酒研倘卖呒
Want to sell wine bottles?
总经埋
President
阿美，试试我为你写的新曲
Ah-mei, try the song I wrote for you
希望你能在演唱会上
I hope
唱给所有需要爱的朋友听
You can sing it for those who need love
特别是你爸爸
Especially for your father
时君迈
Shin Chun-mai
酒，干，倘，卖，呒…
Want.. to…sell…wine…bottle
一样的月光
The same moonlight
一样的照着新店溪
Shines on the same Hsintien River
一样的冬天
The same winter
一样的下着冰冷的雨
Brings the same cold rains
一样的尘埃
The same dust
一样的在风中堆积
Is blown by the same wind
一样的笑容
The same smiles
一样的泪水
The same tears
一样的日子
The same days
一样的我和你
The same you and me
一样的笑容
The same smiles
一样的泪水
The same tears
一样的日子
The same days
一样的我和你
The same you and me
什么时候蛙鸣蝉声都成了记忆
When did the frog croaks become memory
什么时候家乡变得如此的拥挤
When did the land become so crowded
高楼大厦
With tall buildings towering all around
到处耸立
七彩霓虹
And neon signs making the night so harsh
把夜空染得如此的俗气
谁能告诉我，谁能告诉我
Who can tell me? Who can tell?
是我们改变了世界
Did we change the world
还是世界改变了我和你
Or did the world change you and me?
谁能告诉我，谁能告诉我
Who can tell me? Who can tell?
是我们改变了世界
Did we change the world
还是世界改变了我
Or did the world change you and me?
和你
一样的月光
The same moonlight
一样的照着新店溪
Shines on the same Hsintien River
一样的冬天
The same winter
一样的下着冰冷的雨
Brings the same cold rains
一样的尘埃
The same dust
一样的在风中堆积
Is blown by the same wind
一样的笑容
The same smiles
一样的泪水
The same tears
一样的日子
The same days
一样的我和你
The same you and me
一样的笑容
The same smiles
一样的泪水
The same tears
一样的日子
The same days
一样的我和你
The same you and me
阿美…
Ah-mei
快一点啦！快点啊！
Hurry up, hurry up
怎么了？
What's the matter?
快啦！
Hurry
各位观众，各位很抱歉
I'm sorry, ladies and gentlemen
孙瑞琪小姐的家 因为临时发生点小事情
There is something happened in Sun Jui-chi's family
现在，我们请沈妮小姐为各位表演
So now we ask Miss Shen to sing for you
爸…
Dad…
酒矸倘卖呒
Do you have wine bottles to sell?
酒干倘卖呒
多么熟悉的声音
What a familiar sound that is
陪我多少年风和雨
It's been with me day in and day out
从来不需要想起
I never need to think about it
永远也不会忘记
It's something I can never forget
没有天那有地
Without heaven, where would earth be?
没有地那有家
Without earth, where would home be?
没有家那有你
Without home, where would you be?
没有你那有我
Without you, where would I be?
假如你不曾养育我
Without you to raise me
给我温暖的生活
To give me warmth and life
假如你不曾保护我
Without you to protect me
我的命运将会是什么
What would my fate be?
是你抚养我长大
It was you who raised me
陪我说第一句话
Accompany me from my first word saying
是你给我一个家
It was you who gave me a home
让我与你
To share with you, together
共同拥有他
虽然你不能开口说一句话
You cannot open your mouth and speak
却更能明白人世间的黑白与真假
But you know black and white, right and wrong
虽然你不会表达你的真情
You cannot express how you feel
却付出了热枕的生命
You contribute your precious life, though
远处传来你多么熟悉的声音
Your familiar sound, from afar
让我想起你多么慈祥的心灵
Reminds me of your loving soul
什么时候你再回到我的身边
When will you return to my side
让我再和你一起唱
And let us sing together
酒干倘卖呒
Do you have wine bottles to sell?
多么熟悉的声音
What a familiar sound that is
陪我多少年风和雨
It's been with me day in and day out
从来不需要想起
I never need to think about it
永远也不会忘记
It's something I can never forget
没有天那有地
Without heaven, where would earth be?
没有地那有家
Without earth, where would home be?
没有家那有你
Without home, where would you be?
没有你那有我
Without you, where would I be?
多么熟悉的声音
What a familiar sound that is
陪我多少年风和雨
It's been with me day in and day out
从来不需要想起
I never need to think about it
永远也不会忘记
It's something I can never forget
酒干倘卖呒
Do you have wine bottles to sell?